A Finding Aid to the Ellen Hale and Hale Family Papers in the Archives of American Art AAA.halefami
Archives of American Art
Ellen Hale and Hale Family papers
circa 1860-1952
AAA.halefami
Archives of American Art
3 Linear feet
The Ellen Hale and Hale family papers measure 3 linear feet and date from circa 1860 to 1952. Found within the papers are biographical material for Ellen Day and Edward Everett Hale; personal correspondence from Ellen Day and Lillian Westcott Hale; diaries by Ellen Day and Susan Hale; an appraisal of the Hale estate and personal business records for Ellen Day and Edward Everett Hale; printed material; sketchbooks and sketches by Ellen Day and Herbert Dudley Hale; and travel photographs of the Hale family.
Hale, Ellen Day, 1855-1940
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The Ellen Hale and Hale family papers were donated in 1978 and 1984 by Nancy Hale Bowers, the niece of Ellen Day Hale, and the grand-daughter of Edward Everett and Emily P. Hale.
Separated Materials note
Printed books and monographs in the collection were transferred to the National Portrait Gallery Library in 1978.
Related Archival Materials note
The Archives of American Art also holds two collections related to the Hale family, including the Philip Leslie Hale papers and the Edward Everett Hale letter to an unidentified person. Smith College's Sophia Smith Collection also holds papers of the Hale family, including Nathan, Sr., and Sarah Preston Everett Hale; Edward Everett and Emily Perkins Hale; Ellen Day Hale; and Philip and Lilian Westcott Hale..
Existence and Location of Copies note
Portions of this collection are available on 35 mm microfilm reels 2940-2941 and reel 3532 at the Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the papers as described in this finding aid does not reflect the order of the collection on microfilm due to reprocessing.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
Writer, publisher, and clergyman Edward Everett Hale (1822-1909) and his wife, Emily Perkins Hale, were well regarded members of Boston society. After graduating from Boston Latin School at age 13, Hale enrolled directly into Harvard University and graduated second in his class in 1839. He became a licensed Unitarian minister in 1842 and was a church pastor from 1846 to 1899. In the 1860s, Hale began publishing short stories in the Atlantic Monthly, Harper's New Monthly Magazine, and other periodicals. In 1869, he co-founded the Christian Examiner, which later merged with Scribner's Magazine in 1875, and founded Lend a Hand in 1886. He and his wife had one daughter and eight sons. Three of those sons died in childhood, and a fourth, Robert Beverly Hale, died as a young adult.
Writer and artist Susan Hale (1833-1910) was schooled at home by tutors before enrolling in George B. Emerson's school. She was a self-taught artist who learned to paint and draw early in life. In 1872, she traveled to Europe to pursue formal art instruction and, upon her return to Boston, began giving lessons in watercolors. From 1873 to 1885, she maintained a studio at the Boston Art Club, wrote articles for Boston papers, edited literary collections for fundraisers, lectured on popular fiction, and eventually became a literary celebrity. Beginning in the mid-1880s, Hale began traveling the country and abroad giving lectures in the winter and visiting Edward Everett's family in Matunuck, Rhode Island in the summer. In between her travels, she continued to publish books, including a traveling series for young readers, and an instruction book on painting techniques.
Artist and teacher Ellen Day Hale (1854-1939) was the eldest of the Hale children. She received her early art training from her aunt, Susan Hale, and received formal art training from Boston artists William Rimmer, William Morris Hunt, and Helen Knowlton. Hale continued her education at the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, and in 1877, opened a portrait studio where she taught private students. In the early 1880s, Hale traveled through Europe before settling in Paris to study at the Académie Julian for three years. In 1883, she met fellow artist and lifelong companion Gabrielle de Veaux Clements. In 1893, they purchased a home near Gloucester, Massachusetts named "The Thickets," where they opened their studio to women artists and taught various painting, printing, and etching techniques. After the death of her mother, from 1904 to 1909, Hale moved to Washington, D.C. to act as hostess for her father, who had been appointed Chaplain of the U.S. Senate. After her father's death, Hale continued to produce paintings, and together with Clements, summered at the artists' colony at Folly Cove on Cape Ann, Massachusetts, and frequently traveled abroad in the winters.
Arthur Hale (1859-1939) was a general agent for the American Railway Association and an employee of the Pennsylvania Railroad Company. In 1899, he married Camilla Conner, with whom he had one daughter.
Architect Herbert Dudley Hale (1866-1908) graduated from Harvard in 1888 and studied architecture abroad at the École des Beaux Art in Paris, where he graduated among the first in his class. After his return to Boston around the turn of the century, Hale married Margaret Marquand, with whom he had five children, and established the architecture firm Hale and Rogers with James Gamble Rogers.
Writer Robert Beverly Hale (1869-1895) graduated from Harvard in 1892 and published numerous stories and articles in the Atlantic Monthly, Harper's Weekly, and Youth's Companion. Elsie and Other Poems was published in 1894, and Six Stories and Some Verses was published posthumously after Hale's death in 1895.
Artist Lillian Westcott Hale (1881-1963) was the wife of fellow artist Philip Leslie Hale, the third eldest of the Hale children. Hale received a scholarship to attend the Boston Museum School of Fine Arts, where she met Philip and married him halfway through her studies. Hale held her first solo show in 1908, the same year her daughter was born, and continued to produce work for exhibitions through the 1920s. She was the recipient of the 1915 Panama-Pacific Exposition gold medal, the National Academy's Shaw Memorial Prize (1915), and the National Academy of Design's Altman Prize (1927). She continued producing works until her death in 1963.
Scope and Contents note
The Ellen Hale and Hale family papers measure 3 linear feet and date from circa 1860 to 1952. Found within the papers are biographical material for Ellen Day and Edward Everett Hale; personal correspondence from Ellen Day and Lillian Westcott Hale; diaries by Ellen Day and Susan Hale; an appraisal of the Hale estate and personal business records for Ellen Day and Edward Everett Hale; printed material; sketchbooks and sketches by Ellen Day and Herbert Dudley Hale; and travel photographs of the Hale family.
Biographical materials consist of publications related to Edward Everett Hale's 80th birthday celebration; Ellen Day Hale's calling cards, calendar, and engagement books; and Robert Beverly Hale's calendar.
Correspondence is primarily Ellen Day Hale's and Lillian Westcott Hale's personal and business correspondence, and a letter from Margaret C. Hale to Arthur Hale.
Writings include 9 diaries by Ellen Day Hale, 1 diary by Emily P. Hale, and 19 diaries by Susan Hale; an essay by Arthur Hale; Herbert Dudley Hale's word game book; Susan Hale's travel instructions to a niece; and a notebook listing the likes and dislikes of various Hale family members.
Personal business records consist of Edward Everett and Emily P. Hale's account and tax records; Ellen Day Hale's art supply receipts, royalty statements, tax records, and a check register; Lillian Westcott Hale's receipts; and Susan Hale's notes on an appraisal of the Hale estate.
Printed material includes various clippings, invitations, and programs kept by the Hale family, and Ellen Day Hale's travel postcards.
Artwork includes 22 sketchbooks by Ellen Day Hale, 5 sketchbooks by Herbert Dudley Hale; and 7 sketchbooks by other artists.
Photographs are travel snapshots taken during travels in Mexico.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical materials, circa 1875-1925 (6 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, circa 1861-1951 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings, 1878-1933 (0.9 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 4: Personal business records, 1909-1952 (8 folders; Box 2)
Series 5: Printed material, 1862-1933 (5 folders; Box 2)
Series 6: Artwork, circa 1860-1925 (1.5 linear feet; Box 2-3)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1890-1901 (1 folder; Box 3)
Hale, Edward E.; Hale, Emily P.; Hale, Herbert Dudley, 1866-1909; Hale, Lilian Westcott, 1880-1963; Hale, Robert Beverly, 1901-1985; Hale, Susan, 1833-1910; Art, American; Artists--Massachusetts; Diaries; Painters; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Watercolorists; Women painters--Massachusetts
- Biographical Materials, circa 1875-1925; Series 1; 6 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials consist of publications related to Edward Everett Hale's 80th birthday celebration; Ellen Day Hale's calling cards, day calendar, and engagement books; and Robert Beverly Hale's day calendar.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by Hale family member and by document type.
  - Hale, Edward Everett, 80th Birthday Celebration, 1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Addresses and Calling Cards, circa 1875-1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Calendar, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Engagement Books, 1904-1913 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Hale, Robert Beverly, Calendar, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, circa 1861-1951; Series 2; 4 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence consists of Ellen Day Hale's and Lillian Westcott Hale's personal and business correspondence, and a letter regarding family business from Margaret C. Hale to Arthur Hale.
  Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by Hale family member, then alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Hale, Ellen Day, A-Z, 1909-1931 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Illegible and Unknown, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hale, Lillian Westcott, A-Z, 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hale, Margaret C. to Arthur Hale, circa 1895-1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Writings, 1878-1933; Series 3; 0.9 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Writings include 9 diaries by Ellen Day Hale that record daily activities, outgoing expenses, payments received, visits to friends, and a few sketches. Diaries dating from 1900 to 1903 contain the most complete record of entries for each year. In addition, there is 1 diary by Emily P. Hale recording doctors, visitors, and lists of items and 19 daily line diaries by Susan Hale recording visits, appointments, and activities. The series also includes a poem by Arthur Hale; Herbert Dudley Hale's word game book; Susan Hale's travel instructions to a niece visiting Algiers; and a notebook listing the likes and dislikes of various Hale family members.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by Hale family member.
  - Hale, Arthur, "Breakfast Without Tears", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Diaries, 1881-1912 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
  - Hale, Emily P., Diary, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Hale, Herbert Dudley, Word Game Book, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hale, Susan, Diaries, 1878-1895 (Box 1, Folder 18-22)
  - Hale, Susan, Diaries, 1896-1900 (Box 1, Folder 23-27)
  - Hale, Susan, Diaries, 1902-1906 (Box 1, Folder 28-32)
  - Hale, Susan, Diaries, 1907-1909 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Hale, Susan, Travel Instructions to Niece in Algiers, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Notebook, Likes and Dislikes of Hale Family Members, 1861-1865 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Thaxter, Celia, "Sandpiper", circa 1900-1925 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Unknown, "Ruth Putnam", circa 1900-1925 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Personal Business Records, 1909-1952; Series 4; 8 Folders Box 2
  Personal business records consist of Edward Everett and Emily P. Hale's account and tax records; Ellen Day Hale's art supply receipts, royalty statements, tax records, and a check register; Lillian Westcott Hale's receipts; and Susan Hale's notes on an appraisal of the Hale estate.
  - Hale, Edward Everett and Emily P., Account and Estate Records, 1909-1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Hale, Edward Everett and Emily P., Tax Records, 1909-1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Art Supply Receipts, 1909-1929 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Check Register, 1911-1913 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Royalty Statements, 1912-1931 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Tax Records, 1910-1950 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hale, Lillian Westcott, Receipts, 1948-1952 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hale, Susan, Appraisal of Hale Estate, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Printed Material, 1862-1933; Series 5; 5 Folders Box 2
  Printed material includes various clippings, invitations, and programs kept by the Hale family, and Ellen Day Hale's travel postcards.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by Hale family member, then by document type.
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Postcards, circa 1910-1930 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 1902-1903 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Invitations, circa 1905-1925 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Programs, 1862-1933 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1895-1933 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Artwork, circa 1860-1925; Series 6; 1.5 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Artwork includes 22 sketchbooks of landscapes, portraits, and figure studies by Ellen Day Hale; 5 sketchbooks of buildings, landscapes, and figure studies by Herbert Dudley Hale; and 7 sketchbooks by other artists. These include sketchbooks by Margaret White Leslie and H.D. Page, as well as 4 unidentified sketchbooks likely kept by Hale family members. There is also one sketch by Gabrielle de Veaux Clements on the verso of a sketch by Ellen Day Hale.
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by Hale family member, then by artwork subject matter.
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Sketchbook, Figure Studies, circa 1870-1880 (Box 2, Folder 21-23)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Sketchbook, Landscapes, circa 1875-1925 (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Sketchbook, Landscapes and Figure Studies, circa 1880-1910 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Sketchbook, Landscapes and Portrait Studies, circa 1875-1925 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Sketchbook, Landscapes and Portrait Studies, circa 1875-1925 (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Sketchbook, Landscapes, Portraits, and Animal Studies, circa 1880-1910 (Box 3, Folder 4-6)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Sketchbook, Landscapes, Portraits, and Figure Studies, circa 1880-1910 (Box 3, Folder 7-10)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Sketchbook, Portrait Studies, circa 1900-1910 (Box 3, Folder 11-12)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Sketchbook, Portraits and Figure Studies, circa 1880-1910 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Hale, Ellen Day, Sketches, circa 1880-1910 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Hale, Herbert Dudley, Sketchbook, Building and Figure Studies, circa 1885-1900 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Hale, Herbert Dudley, Sketchbook, Figure Studies, 1885 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Hale, Herbert Dudley, Sketchbook, Landscapes and Figure Studies, circa 1885-1900 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
  - Hale, Herbert Dudley, Sketchbook, Landscapes, Buildings, and Figure Studies, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Hale, Herbert Dudley, Sketchbook Cover, circa 1885-1900 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Hale, Herbert Dudley, Sketches, circa 1885-1900 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Hainde, Sketchbook, Landscapes and Figure Studies, circa 1885-1920 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Leslie, Margaret White, Sketchbook, Landscapes and Figure Studies, 1879 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Page, H.D., Sketchbook, Landscapes, Portraits, and Figure Studies, 1868-1876 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Unidentified Artist, Sketchbook, Landscapes, circa 1872-1892 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Unidentified Artist, Sketchbook, Shapes, Animals, and Figure Studies, circa 1860-1889 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- Photographs, circa 1890-1901; Series 7; 1 Folders Box 3
  Photographs are travel snapshots taken during travels in Mexico.
  Photographs are arranged by the original album collation.
  - Travel Photographs, circa 1890-1901 (Box 3, Folder 27)